software engineering radio episode 51
designed by contract
welcome to a new episode of software
engineering radio this time it's Michael
and Arnaud on the microphone I'm
actually going to interview Arno on the
sign by contract
yeah great to have you listen so I know
what is designed by contract where does
it come from the design by contract is
actually a paradigm of thinking about
software design it's a way of thinking
about interfaces about the separation of
interfaces and implementations and the
term design by contract is something
Bertrand Meyer came up with in the 80s
he wrote the book object-oriented
software construction we'll have it in
the show notes he also came up with a
programming language eiffel which
implements these concepts so there are
implementations that support design by
contract but the actual thing is it's a
way of thinking about design the idea is
that you have abstract data types and
these abstract data types are sort of
interfaces I mean the usual program
languages just interfaces that have
these and the interfaces are not just
the signatures of the methods but they
also contain a contain and in the
implementation independent specification
of what they do so they sort of offer a
contract which is in a way the very
natural to think about things I mean if
we have a let's say we have a collection
interface or a collection type and we
have an ADD method and we have a remove
method and we have a get method then
obviously we expect the get method to
return nothing in the beginning because
the collection is empty and once we add
something then the get method returns on
what we added before so this is goes
beyond the signatures it's sort of the
meaning behind the signatures and design
by contract is a way of formalizing this
but it is a helpful mindset to have even
if you do not have explicit um support
in the program
the programming language that we that
you use so what is a contract and and
here exactly well the contract arm is
actually it's a metaphor from everyday
life
um contract something we are all
familiar with um the idea is that you
interact with an object you as the
corner and the object as the thing that
you call agree on a contract and the
object is the party that offers the
contract and you can take it or leave it
sort of the idea is the met every method
on the object guarantees to do something
to yield certain results to make certain
modifications if you as the caller meet
your part of the contract if you meet
the preconditions that you well that the
object requires um the important thing
is that that that as in everyday life
the contract is a bi-directional thing
it's not just the object does something
and I'm it is the caller I'm out of the
loop nor is it I am as the caller need
to do everything in the object can do
whatever it wants but well if I rent a
room I get the keys I get to live in it
if I pay the rent so it really it goes
both ways this is the way of thinking
about it what is the result of a brie
and post condition when it gets
evaluated is it is it just the boolean
or is it something more how what what is
the result of what can be the result of
a pre and a post condition well as I
said pre and post conditions are
actually boolean expressions every
method has a list of preconditions which
is a list of expressions that yield the
boolean this list of preconditions must
evaluate to true with the things that I
used to call and then the resist of post
conditions also a list of boolean
expressions and the object guarantees
that if I meet the preconditions the
list of post conditions will evaluate to
true after the thing was called um I
think in the
example would be helpful here let's say
we have a very simple method square root
that takes a double obviously the
precondition well the typical
precondition would be the parameter X
must be greater or equal zero because
dealing with real numbers um nothing
else makes sense and the post condition
would be that the result that is
returned by the method multiplied by
itself is um x well sort of
I mean it is never exactly X so the post
condition is formalized so it would say
um the difference between the square of
the result and X is less than a very
small number so you sort of give the
precision with which square root
guarantees to perform the calculation
and this actually shows one of the
values the valuable sides of actually
formalizing post conditions and
preconditions because it makes it xsplit
makes the precision of the operation
explicit in the in the contract in the
signature which is great for many
applications um most of the time you
check functional post conditions
particularly like um well this um the
value that calculated let's calculate it
conforms to certain conditions that's
the thing in some circumstances you well
there are some um some people who doing
work on non-functional post conditions
like the number of processor cycles that
a or an operation takes that sort of
thing but usually it's functional post
conditions plant functional
preconditions on what kind of data do
debris and post conditions operate I
guess they operate under parameters they
operate under internal state but what if
is if the the object doesn't have any
state what about a stateless object yeah
excellent excellent point um of course
it's important to know or to specify
what what sort of data the pre post
conditions can operate on actually the
obvious thing
is for pre-established precondition is
the operator obvious thing is the
parameters that you pass in mmm which
which I mean with the square-root
example is obvious I mean you can
obviously this parameter must not be
null or that parameter must be arranged
from 2 or this string must have a
minimum length of such-and-such so these
are the typical things you often check
with assertions it's a typical thing the
code requires make certain requirements
on the parameters another set of data
that the on the precondition is allowed
to operate on is visible state public
state of the object as we said in the
beginning designer contract is about
interfaces not about implementations so
all state that is accessible through the
interface is um can can appear in a
precondition um so for example let's go
back to the collection example let's say
we we have a method size which makes the
number of elements in the collection
part of the public interface and then we
have the let's say get first method and
um get that same the contract for this
collection says you're not permitted or
get first we'll return now or well let's
make it simple get first must not be
called if the collection is empty so the
precondition could be size greater than
zero this is not the only way to do it
there are good reasons for not having
this precondition but it's one possible
way of specifying it and that would mean
no one is permitted to call get first on
this collection if the collection is
empty
let's say it is a stack and you have the
pop operation but there it is very
common not to be permitted to call pop
if the collection is empty so accessing
the internal state through the public
interface is permitted in writing down
the preconditions but it is not possible
to
a reference internal state because as I
said preconditions post conditions are
part of the interface and the interface
does not know anything or and should and
must be independent of the
implementation that's the idea for the
post conditions things are a little bit
more complicated you can again arm in
the post conditions reference the
parameters as in the square-root example
you said the result multiplied by itself
is the same roughly the same as the
parameter X that we passed in you can
also access the result of the operation
which is obviously necessary and then
there are things you can access the
state of the object before the operation
was called and you can access the state
of the object after the operation was
caught let's say in the collection
example we have a method at IDI which
adds something to the collection then
one of the post conditions would be the
size after the operation is one bigger
than the size at the beginning of the
operation so this is another thing that
well that's something that is added in
complexity and possibilities for the
post conditions that you do not need in
preconditions okay so before we go into
more detail on undersigned by contract
what are the benefits of it well the
benefit first of all is to to specify to
have a formal specification of what code
does um I mean we all know that comments
are sort of good
many people say write comments comments
are great many people say code must be
comment in order to be understandable
but we also know that comments have a
tendency to be outdated comments about
what in a method does are not
automatically reliable or maybe they
were inaccurate to start with maybe they
some changes were made later on and the
comments did not reflect them designed
by contract um is a formal way of
writing down the
um the watch but a method does what
interphase is all about and if you have
tool support for it we will get to that
later
then during execution time the
conditions are checked so the first and
biggest benefit is pre and post
conditions never get outdated they are
always up-to-date documentation about
what in an interface actually does what
operations on the interface do um it's
something like on the signature checking
by the compiler if you change the name
of an operation all the rest of the code
automatically does not compile there's
an automatic automatic check on that
this change needs to reflect analog
lines designer contra is something like
that but at the behavior level goes
deeper um
but of course there's a downside writing
design by contract
um specifications writing preconditions
post conditions is work um does take
some effort it does take some getting
used to and the main benefit is there at
least if you if you want to take the
effort of really being formal about it
the main effort is there if you have
some sort of tool support will have some
some common tools listed on the on the
website and we'll mentioned some of them
later as well I could imagine that the
sign back contract is not useful for for
every kind of object even if it has
stayed it might just not make sense to
specify pre and post conditions or let
me put it differently it might be
impossible to specify pre and post
conditions for example in a user
interface or the like it's hard to
specify a precondition well this button
appeared or this button now looks is
pressed or things like that and what are
you thinking about that well interesting
point let's let's take a closer look at
that because um yeah it's quite
interesting I mean the closer you get to
the borders of a system the more
difficult these sort of things get the
more equal to unit test is more
difficult to write pre and post
conditions but let's let's take the
concrete example let's say we have a
graphical
interface what what sort of interface
would you imagine that is hard to to
write contracts for for example when I
try to visualize something I have no
means to then query my screen whether
this has actually been displayed for
example okay that would be the interface
to the to the GUI system sort of you say
you make an API call display the button
and you have no no way of actually
calling an operation that tells you if
the button was actually displayed right
yes true you suck there are definitely
limits there but um that is a limitation
of the user interface the excellent
point and definitely if you use existing
API eyes those usually are not come with
um with contracts but with the user
interface you have you are the one
calling the interface so the contracts
are always part of the interface that is
being called in tool support must be in
the component that you are calling so um
yes there are limitations there but the
limitation is basically the interface is
not yours so when the interface is not
used you have no way of actually
implementing these contracts or contract
checks on the interface but yes that's
definitely a limitation
how does design by contract relate to
inheritance I guess it can be quite
complicated what are what are the rules
here that I would have to obey when when
bringing inheritance into the play yeah
again excellent point because
inheritance is one of the really complex
and weird side effects having aspects of
programming with object or head
languages but again it's part of the fun
the problem here is polymorphism um if
you have an interface with several
possible implementations so we have one
super type and several subtypes of this
and you have a contract on the supertype
then you as the caller do not know which
X which concrete type which actual
implementation or which snap type of
this interface you are dealing with you
have a let's say you have the list
interface um which just implements a
collection then you do not know and
should not know if this is just a list
based on an array or if it's a doubly
linked list or maybe even a an
arbitrarily huge list that is backed by
a database the idea is that you have
note that they are functionally
equivalent so that this is the idea of
abstracting the supertype out this is
what probably morphism is all about but
abstract data types are all about and so
this sort of means that subtypes must
inherit all the contracts of the super
types I mean if I am dealing with the
list I want to be sure that every
concrete implementation of list actually
conforms to the guarantees that list
made this is what makes this what makes
the the contracts valuable how so the
the basic point of foundation of the
interaction between inheritance and his
under contract is subtypes inherits all
preconditions and all post conditions
from the super types this is sort of the
baseline which is necessary for the
whole concept to work there is however
the opportunity to for a subtype to
provide a better contract than a in the
super type so for example um the let's
say let's stay with this collection
example I suggested that a collection
has a get method and or yeah let's say
is concrete is deck interface has a pop
method and this pop method in the
interface there's the precondition you
must not call pop if the stack is empty
a concrete implementation might relax
this precondition insane
if you use my implementation you are
permitted to call pop if you if the
Cutlass in the stack is anti empty
you'll just reach to every return zero
which is a relaxation of a precondition
which is staying with the contract
example an improvement of the contract
the eye is the one dealing with the
object I am required to do less another
thing is the arm the operation or the
the concrete type or the subtype can
provide additional post conditions for
example the square root arm or method in
the super type let's say it um calculate
the square root with a certain accuracy
and the subtype might provide better
accuracy in calculating the square root
and express that in the contract so this
sort of improvement of the contracts is
okay but obviously improving the
contract means that subtypes must
conform to all capri and all post
conditions of the super track of the
super types contract so when I'm dealing
with the super type have referenced you
super happy and I call operations on it
I can rely on the super types contracts
and subtypes may provide better than
that but um definitely not worse this is
actually quite important or this is one
point where tool support comes really
important because um without a tool
support there's actually no simple way
to keep the checks synchronized if I for
example do things with assertions um
then I have some assertions in the super
type and the subtype um to do the same
assertions but they need to be copy and
pasted basically so it's very very
difficult to maintain um
manually maintained design the contract
in the face of inheritance
in summary basically the and inheriting
type has to have the same precondition
possibly weaker and the same post
condition possibly stronger exactly yes
it demands less of the of the caller and
can demand more of itself this is one
very difficult point of the evolution of
api's because a well especially in the
service oriented architecture thing but
also we in component oriented
programming in general it is one of the
tough questions is how to handle the
evolution of api's what if an API of if
you know interface changes a published
interface changes how to deal with that
if you add operations if you want to
change the name of put operation if you
want to add or remove parameters
whatever this sort of raises the bar one
further because um even if the the
signatures stays the same you need the
contracts can change over time and the
contracts are part of the interface so
you need to apply the interface
evolution the component interface
evolution are mechanisms to design by
contract contracts as well it's
sometimes tough in arm in practice but
it's definitely it's well it's play
necessary it's just with the price that
you pay for um for having published
api's they are painful to maintain but
we all know the uses so it's worth it
um there is however a big benefit of
having explicit design the contract
annotations on the interfaces and that
is we actually see that the interface
has changed even though all signatures
of all operations stay the same so um if
you do not have design by contract you
may not notice but you still have the
problems if someone calls and the
semantics of an operation changed the
obviously um you're in trouble and
design the contract helps you to catch
this sort of problem earlier on next up
question what about exceptions
I guess they they cannot be easily
formulated with pre and post conditions
especially not with post conditions
you're really touching all the tough
points great
well of course exceptions that are being
thrown must be part of designer contract
otherwise it just wouldn't be mature
enough for practical work exceptions are
here to stay and they're important well
you well mainly the way of propagating
errors in most systems so yes
December contract just deal with
exceptions and basically exceptions are
just a special sort of return value I
mean they're not return in the sense of
a return statement and you have them in
the as a return type but still they are
treated in the same way so one post
condition might say if you have if you
call pop on an empty stack this or that
exception is thrown which is a post
condition so it's one way for an
operation to terminate and that's okay
for for more reference on this I suggest
you listen to the error handling
episodes they go into this also with
regard to designer country a little bit
it is however very very important to to
keep a post condition that an exception
is being thrown apart from the caller
not meeting a precondition they have
very easy to mix up and it's very very
important to keep them separated clearly
separated in your mind if a caller does
not meet a precondition this is a bug
always and no no discussion about that
it's a bank if a caller does not meet a
precondition because that was
preconditions are about Bertrille Maya
once said if you use December contract
and a column does not meet a
precondition it's okay for the system to
crash basically well crash in a graceful
that helps debugging that sort of thing
but preconditions are not for sort not
to be caught later on so oh I didn't
meet the precondition so I'll I'll do
that and try something else
preconditions are hard they are a hard
barrier that you have to pass through
however if it's very different for a
post condition that says if under these
and that circumstances and exception is
is thrown because that is sort of valid
behavior you met all the preconditions
as a caller and the quote that you call
decided or well it laid its card on the
table sort of saying if if you if these
and that conditions are there then
obviously I will call I will throw this
or that exception which is then
catchable and you can base decisions in
the calling code on these exception
anything at all but it's a very very
important distinction between these two
okay so when you say it's a back then
this leads instantly my thoughts to the
idea that design by contract is mostly
useful at development time when I didn't
ship my my system when I ship my system
to my customer and I have the the tool
or the technique of design by contract
still enabled is it a good or a bad
thing that the system crashes oh they're
very very good question actually I would
say this is something similar to having
assertions turned on or off in
production there are some contexts where
it is desirable to leave them on for
many business applications for example I
would say it's a good idea to keep them
on because well there is um or if a
precondition is not met the behavior of
the system is sort of undefined and you
usually want to avoid that so being no
and obviously this is not about crashing
the system in real systems it there's
often a more robust way of handling this
but still um sort of a hard abort of
this thread and notification to the
thread scheduler whatever um that this
operation really really failed that sort
of thing
I think yeah that is quite helpful even
during production because um yeah you
you really find your bugs that's the
idea of it um there are however
applications that say a pacemaker in a
heart or the flight control software for
the Space Shuttle so this sort of life
critical mission critical software um
where it is well where it is better to
go on with inconsistent with
inconsistent state then then failing the
process altogether
I think it's trade-off but I would seem
to leave them on in many systems okay
most languages do not support design by
contract directly so so what chances do
I have to use design by contract as a
means for for development first of all
first opportunity you to use them is
switch to isil no just joking ISIL as a
language has the support and it's a
great language to look at if you were to
understand the concept but of course
this is not a really practical approach
because you don't do your projects and
eiffel usually they're constraints on
that the good reasons not to use it um
well the first thing you can do is
actually just write the comments in a
more or less formalized way design the
contract is a very valuable tool even if
you just have the mindset if you think
about your interfaces not only in terms
of the signatures of the operations but
also in what do these operations do what
what requirements do they pose on the
caller and what guarantees do they
provide um when they are being called
this is sort of the first step getting
into the mindset um another step you can
go beyond that is um there are - there
are tools form well for quite a lot of
mainstream languages for C C++ for Java
I think for Ruby as well probably for
for basically all of the mainstream
languages now but those are the
languages of which I heard that of the
tools or have seen them
and they are well the super sub C++
approach is based on macros usually
macro expansion in Java it is Javadoc
comments that are processed by a
preprocessor and so the quote is
instrumented there are tools that you
can actually use and yet it's a great
way of doing this of course this has
some influence on your arm built in on
your development environment on your
build process and this sort of thing but
that's definitely a way that you can go
but if you don't want to go that effort
or another tool another library you can
always start with using assertions so
that is very very limited in scope so
design by contract seems to be similar
to assertions where is the difference
worst personal limit um the the thing
where they where there are where they go
close together is you have conditions
that are checked at runtime and these
conditions that are checked at runtime
sort of abort the thread in a in a way
that is not intended to be handled
saying this is a bug preconditions are
actually quite easy to implement using
design the contract you can have
assertions at the beginning of an
operation checking for parameter
validity calling or comparing or
checking some constraints on the size if
you have a pop operation for a stack you
need to have an assertion that says size
must be greater than zero so
preconditions are quite easy to
implement using assertions although you
do not have inheritance if you have a
super type you cannot specify surgeons
in an interface in an abstract type you
can only have them in the implementation
and you have no support for propagating
them for checking that subtypes have the
same contracts as the super types the
thing becomes even more difficult for
for post conditions and the reason for
that is that post conditions oftentimes
compare the state of the object
the beginning of the operation to the
state of the object at the end of the
operation and having that sort of thing
requires the use of temporary local
variables that are initialized at the
beginning and then read at the end of
the operation this is very very hard to
maintain manually um you can do this but
well technically of course you can do it
I mean the programming language that you
use is capable of it but it's very very
hard to maintain it's not very practical
so basically checking post conditions is
where this is where assertions fail
where where surgeons are not enough comp
or where the big benefit of having tool
for example contract compared to
assertions is we just learned that I can
improve the quality of my software using
pre and post conditions so is it valid
to say well using pre and post
conditions I save all the automated
testing well there are some people who
say that actually um but I wouldn't
agree I think they go very well together
cause them the scope and the time when
they are run is different pre and post
conditions are checked at a run time
whereas unit tests of the whatever unit
family type um they are checked at Build
time so you you often often you have a
desire to find your bugs during build
time as early as possible or as many
bugs as possible before the system goes
into manual testing or into production
but if you have so if you have pre and
post conditions um this makes the
writing of unit tests simpler you sort
of just um call your operations go
through the business code and the pre
and post conditions do much of the
assertion checking that you have would
otherwise have in your unit tests but um
they're not a replacement for all the
assertion checking that the unit tests
have and of course you have to write the
fixtures and be clever about some things
writing the tests still so they go
actually they're complementary um they
go together quite well
this kind of glosses our episode would
you mind summing up what we just learned
as a closing sure design by contract is
about um is a way of thinking about
interfaces about abstract types and
thinking about them not only in terms of
operations and their signatures but also
in terms of the semantics behind those
operations that is it's not only the
name of the operation and the name names
and types of the parameters and the
return type but also under what
circumstances does this operation do
what um and what do i as a caller have
to do for this operation to do what it
promises to do this is the key thing
about design by contract and that's the
only thing you remember from this
episode that's great but you get
additional benefit if you have to
support for this um can there are ways
of writing formalized um conditions to
annotations to the operations depending
on the tool depending on the programming
language and then these are checked at
runtime and this is obviously additional
benefit and these these tools also
ensure that contracts are maintained in
inheritance hierarchies they ensure that
every subtype program has proffers
offers at least as good a contract as
the supertype does so these are
additional benefits you get if you use
tools but even if you just keep this
mindset of an operation is more than
just a signature it is a contract it is
a list of guarantees that I as a caller
have to provide and then the object
guarantees to do certain other things um
and this is not part of the
implementation but it is part of the
interface this way of thinking about
interfaces about interface operations in
terms of contracts is really valuable
even if you don't use tools great Thank
You Arnaud for explaining design by
contract Russ thank you Michael
thanks everybody for listening here you
next week bye bye bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Cowley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details